Guide to the Pearl Primus Collection, 1920-1994
American Dance Festival Archives
Pearl Primus collection 1920-1994
American Dance Festival Archives Box 90772 Durham, North Carolina, 27708-0772 USA Phone: 919-684-6402 Fax: 919-684-5459 Email: adfarchives@americandancefestival.org
Primus, Pearl
20.4 linear feet Extent: 20650 Items
Pearl Primus (1919-1994) was an African-American dancer, choreographer, anthropologist, and teacher. Collection includes materials created or collected by Primus and by others dating from circa 1920 to 1994, including correspondence, writings, legal documents, research and teaching materials, clippings, programs, printed materials, photographs, sound recordings, films, videos, and artifacts.
ADF.012
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Patrons must sign the Acknowledgement of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights form before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Access to film, videotapes, or audiotapes in this collection requires the use of reference copies. To arrange for the creation of reference copies, if none exist, please contact American Dance Festival Archives.
Provenance
The Pearl Primus Collection was received by the American Dance Festival Archives as gifts in 2000.
Biographical Note
Pearl Primus (1919-1994) was an African-American dancer, choreographer, anthropologist, and teacher. She was born in Trinidad in 1919 and raised in New York City, where she attended Hunter High School from 1933 to 1937. Primus received her BA in biology from Hunter College in 1940, where she had been preparing for a career in medicine. Her career goals changed, however, when she began dancing with the New Dance Group, an integrated, politically progressive dance collective. Primus made her professional dance debut in New York City in 1943. She began performing at the Café Society, an integrated nightclub, and in 1944 she gave her first solo recital, performing to poetry and the music of folksinger Josh White. Later that year she traveled the American South, where she worked as a cotton-picker in order to learn more about the plight of African-Americans in the region, an experience that later inspired several dances.
In 1946 Primus took graduate classes in education at Columbia University and performed professionally with her own company and with the New York revival of Showboat and the Chicago Civic Opera production of The Emperor Jones. In 1949, Primus traveled to Africa on a grant from the Julius Rosenwald Foundation. She lived with tribes in Nigeria and the Belgian Congo, among others, observing and recording African dances, ceremonies, and other cultural activities and aspects of society.
In August 1950 Primus married Yael Woll and formally enrolled at Columbia University. She toured internationally with her company and as a solo artist, performing in England for King George IV and Queen Mary in 1951, at the inauguration of Liberian President William V. S. Tubman in 1952, and with her company in Israel and France in 1952.
In early 1953 Primus separated from Woll. The following summer, Primus continued her studies of dance in Trinidad and met dancer and choreographer Percival Borde. They married in 1954, and Primus gave birth to their son, Onwin, in January 1955. Primus and Borde continued to perform and teach together until Borde's death in 1979.
Primus received her MA in educational sociology from New York University and was awarded a grant from the Rebecca Harkness Foundation to study in Africa in 1959. Upon her return to the U.S. in 1963, Primus founded the Primus-Borde School of Dance, where she developed methods of cross-cultural education through dance. Primus tested these methods in New York City elementary schools from 1965 through 1968 and published her findings for the U.S. Department of Education in 1968. Her phonograph record, Pearl Primus' Africa, was recorded to assist teachers in elementary and high schools.
In 1969, while pursuing a doctorate in anthropology at NYU, Primus was appointed professor at Hunter College. In asserting that dance was an international language, Primus became the first NYU student to use dance to fulfill the language requirement. After completing her dissertation on the use of sculpture to acculturate children in the Mano tribe of Liberia, Primus received her PhD in anthropology in 1978. She began the Pearl Primus Dance Language Institute to promote her blending of African-American, Caribbean, and African influences with modern dance and ballet techniques. Percival Borde died on August 31, 1979 in New York.
Primus was appointed director of the Cora P. Maloney College at State University of New York-Buffalo in 1982, where she taught for two years. From 1984 to 1990, Primus served as a professor of ethnic studies and artist-in-residence at the Five College Consortium in Massachusetts. In the following years, Primus was in residency at Howard University, taught at NYU, and worked towards the founding of the Pearl Primus Dance Arts Foundation.
Primus received many awards, including a Star of Africa decoration from the Liberian government and the Scroll of Honor from the National Council of Negro Women. In 1991, President George H. W. Bush awarded Primus the National Medal of Arts for "outstanding contributions to the excellence, growth, support and availability of the arts in the United States." Primus' other awards include the Distinguished Service Award from the Association of American Anthropologists in 1985, an honorary doctorate from Spelman College in 1988, the American Dance Festival's first Balasaraswati/Joy Ann Dewey Beinecke Chair for Distinguished Teaching in 1991 and, posthumously, the American Dance Festival/Scripps Award for Lifetime Achievement in Choreography. Primus died in New Rochelle, NY, in 1994.
Collection Overview
Collection includes materials created or collected by Primus and by others dating from circa 1920 to 1994, including correspondence, writings, legal documents, research and teaching materials, clippings, programs, printed materials, photographs, sound recordings, films, videos, and artifacts.
Collection Arrangement
The Pearl Primus Collection is organized into eight series: Correspondence, Subject Files, Dissertation Materials, Printed Materials, Photographs, Moving Images, Sound Recordings, and Artifacts.
Subject Headings
Primus, Pearl; African American dance; Choreographers -- United States; Dance -- United States; Ethnology -- Africa; Modern dance -- United States
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence, 1937-1994 and undated
  - Pearl Primus, 1937-1938, 1947-1994 and undated, .75 linear feet (Box 1)
    Arranged chronologically
    Includes letters to Primus from family, friends, fans, and academic colleagues, and letters from Primus to company members, government officials, educators, and funding organizations, among others. Writings, project proposals, invitations, and printed materials are also present. There is extensive correspondence from 1949 documenting her experience in Africa, especially in Liberia. Other significant correspondence includes letters written in 1953 to Primus from her future husband, Percival Borde. Correspondence from the 1980s reflects Primus' professional activities as a faculty member at SUNY-Albany, SUNY-Buffalo, and the Five College Dance Department.
  - Onwin Primus-Borde, 1987, 1 folder, 1 item (Box 1)
  - Percival Borde, 1956, 1962-1964, 1 folder (Box 1)
- Subject Files, 1934-1994 and undated, 4 linear feet (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically
  Contains materials created or collected by Primus (and occasionally Borde) including correspondence, printed materials, notes, writings, and other materials. Prevalent are materials from Primus' second trip to Africa, including receipts, expense lists, notes, writings, poetry, project proposals, and memorabilia. Borde's activities in Africa during this time are documented by similar materials, as well as diaries, travel documents, and permits. Materials related to Primus' academic career, from high school student to college professor, are in the Notebooks and Notes subject folders. Course materials primarily date to Primus' tenure on the faculty of the Five College Dance Department and at SUNY-Buffalo's Cora P. Maloney College. Primus' daily life is characterized by personal notes, schedules, itineraries, and six diaries, which contain Primus' daily "to do" lists as well as shopping and correspondence lists and some financial information. Occasionally they contain brief musings or phrases of poetry she composed.
  - Africa, 1949, 1960 and undated (Box 1)
  - Africa, Liberia: Invitations and Programs, Presidential Events, 1949, 1952 (Box OS1)
  - Africa, Liberia: Liberian Cultural Affairs Committee, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Africa, Nigeria: International Club Brochure, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Africa, Printed Materials: The Liberian Age (11 issues), 1948-1949 (Box OS1)
  - Africa, Printed Materials: New York Times supplement on Liberia, July 25, 1965 (Box OS1)
  - Africa, Printed Materials: New York Times Magazine, March 14, 1965 (Box OS1)
  - Africa, Printed Materials: Sierra Leone Trade Industry & Travel, 1959 (Box OS1)
  - Africa, Printed Materials: Weekend Telegraph (U.K.), 1964 (Box OS1)
  - Alma John Workshops, 1984 (Box 1)
  - American Dance Festival (Black Tradition in American Modern Dance project), 1988 (Box 1)
  - Artwork by Primus, circa 1955 (Box OS3)
  - Artwork of Primus (illegible signature), undated (Box OS3)
  - Awards and Certificates, circa 1935, 1970-1988 (Box 1)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1985 (Box OS2)
  - Barbados Dance Theatre and Five College Dance Department Exchange, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Barbados Workshops, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information and Resumes, 1968-1990 and undated (Box 1)
  - Borde, Onwin: Awards and Certificates, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Borde, Percival: Dorothea Towles, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Borde, Percival: Nigeria, Trinidad and Tobago Cultural Society, 1962 (Box OS1)
  - Borde, Percival: Writings, circa 1962 (Box 1)
  - Borde, Percival: Writings, Diaries, 1962 (Box OS1)
  - Children's Theatre Company, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Contact Information (address lists and business cards), undated (Box 1)
  - Contact Information (address lists), undated (Box OS1)
  - Contracts and Correspondence, Lordly and Dame, 1986-1989 (Box OS1)
  - Course Materials, circa 1963-1987 (Box 1)
  - Course Materials: Student Papers, 1988, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Course Materials: Syllabi, 1984-1994 (Box 1)
  - Course Materials: Syllabus, 1985 (Box OS1)
  - Course Materials: Test and Lecture Notes, 1987, 1991 and undated (Box 1)
  - The Dance Project (WNET), 1987-1990 (Box 1)
  - Everybody's Creative Arts Center (CitiCentre Dance Theatre), 1984-1986 (Box 1)
  - Restricted: Greeting card by Primus, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Reference Copy: Greeting card by Primus, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Howard University Residency, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Hunter College Employment, 1969-1973 (Box 1)
  - Italy, Oct.-Dec. 1956 (Box 1)
  - Kwanzaa Speech Notes, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Kwanzaa Student Project, 1983 (Box OS1)
  - Ledger, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Legal Affairs: Contracts, 1951-1989 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents: Eviction Proceedings, 1963, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents: Immigration, 1937, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Legal Documents: Marriage Certificate and Divorce Decrees, 1961 (Box OS1)
  - Legal Documents: Onwin Borde, 1955, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Legal Documents: Permits and Licenses, 1951, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia, 1940-1976 and undated (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia: Postcards, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1948-1986 and undated (Box 2)
  - National Council for Culture and Art, 1980 (Box 2)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1985-1994 (Box 2)
  - New York University, Fifth International Festival, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Notebook, circa 1951 (Box 2)
  - Notebooks: Africa, circa 1958-1963 (Box 2)
  - Notebook, circa 1965 (Box 2)
  - Notebook, 1977-1981 (Box 2)
  - Notebook, circa 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Notebook, circa 1992 (Box 2)
  - Notes: Africa, circa 1949-1960 (Box 2)
  - Notes: Africa, Bushongo and Watusi, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: African-American History and Heritage, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: African-American Women, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: African Art, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: Anthropology, undated (Box OS1)
  - Notes: Caribbean, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: Choreography, Dance, circa 1950-1959 (Box OS1)
  - Notes: Choreography, Dance, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: Cora P. Maloney College, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: Dance Presentation for Children Study, undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: First African Performing Arts Center (Konoma Kende), undated (Box 2)
  - Notes: First African Performing Arts Center (Konoma Kende), undated (Box OS1)
  - Notes: Personal, undated (Box OS1)
  - Notes: Personal and Professional (2 folders), circa 1950-1980 (Box 2)
  - Pearl Primus-Percival Borde School of Dance, 1968 (Box OS1)
  - Poetry, Music, Lyrics by Primus Project Proposals: African-Caribbean-American Dance-Arts Center, circa 1955 (Box OS1)
  - Project Proposals: African-Caribbean-American Dance-Arts Center, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Project Proposals: First African Dance Theatre, circa 1958 (Box 2)
  - Project Proposals: Pearl Primus Dance Language Institute, undated (Box 2)
  - Project Proposals by Primus, 1955-1989 and undated (Box 2)
  - Project Proposals by Others, 1987 and undated (Box 2)
  - Publishing Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Rebekah Harkness Foundation Tour of Africa: Financial, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Rebekah Harkness Foundation Tour of Africa: Primus, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Rebekah Harkness Foundation Tour of Africa: Borde, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Rebekah Harkness Foundation Tour of Africa: Proposal and Description, 1962 and undated (Box OS1)
  - Receipts, 1952-1957 and undated (Box 2)
  - Receipts: Nigeria, Dec. 1948-Apr. 1949 (Box 2)
  - Receipts: Belgian Congo, May-Aug. 1949 (Box 2)
  - Schedules and Itineraries, 1949-circa 1992 and undated (Box 2)
  - School Essays, 1935-circa 1940 and undated (Box 2)
  - School Notes: Biology, undated (Box 2)
  - School Notes: Biology, Botany, 1938 and undated (Box 2)
  - School Notes: Dance, undated (Box 2)
  - School Notes: English Literature, undated (Box 2)
  - School Notes: Physical Education, 1938 and undated (Box 2)
  - School Notes: Primitive Art, 1953 (Box 2)
  - School Notes: Psychology, undated (Box 2)
  - School Notes: Roman History, undated (Box 2)
  - SISA (Sisterhood in Support of Sisters in South Africa), 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Spelman College Inauguration and Symposium, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Spiritual Baptists, Granville Williams, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
  - Symposium: The Struggle for Liberation in Southern Africa, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Travel Documents (including passports and permits), 1948-1963 (Box 2)
  - White, Josh, 1983-1984 and undated (Box 2)
  - Writings, undated (Box 2)
  - Writings: Africa, 1962 (Box OS1)
  - Writings: Africa, undated (Box 2)
  - Writings: African Dance, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Writings: An Evaluation Report on Cultural Enrichment Through the Dance, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Writings: Dance, undated (Box 2)
  - Restricted: Writings: Diary, circa 1943-1949 (Box 5)
  - Reference Copy: Writings: Diary, circa 1943-1949 (Box 2)
  - Writings: Diary, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Writings: Diary, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Restricted: Writings: Diary, circa 1956 (Box 5)
  - Reference Copy: Writings: Diary, circa 1956 (Box 3)
  - Writings: Diary, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Writings: Diary, circa 1960 (Box 3)
  - Writings: Poetry, Lyrics, and Music, undated (Box 3)
  - Restricted: Writings: Tree Worship, 1934 (Box 5)
  - Reference Copy: Writings: Tree Worship, 1934 (Box 3)
  - Restricted: Writings: Diary by M. Hull, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Writings: By Others, 1960-1991 and undated (Box 3)
  - Writings: By Others about Primus, 1979, 1982 and undated (Box 3)
  - Writings: Poetry, Lyrics, and Music by Others, 1928, 1965, and undated (Box 3)
  - Writings: Woll, Yael, English Composition notebook, 1938 (Box 3)
- Dissertation Materials, 1959-1977 and undated, .5 linear foot, 21 folders (Box 3)
  Proposal drafts are followed by drafts of chapters or sections, followed by folders devoted to illustrations, bibliographies, research materials, and correspondence. Drafts of chapters and sections are presented in the same order as the table of contents of the most complete draft of the dissertation. The identification of some materials as part of Primus' dissertation proposal is sometimes uncertain; likewise, some materials filed as a draft of a chapter of the dissertation may possibly be a draft of proposal chapters or sections.
  Contains various drafts of Primus' doctoral dissertation at New York University entitled "A Study of Sculpture-Dance as a Factor in the Enculturation of the Mano People of Liberia, West Africa, Between 1948 and 1963." The final version of the dissertation is not included. Also included are photocopies of research materials and illustrations used in the dissertation. Primus began her research in Liberia during the tour sponsored by Rosenwald Foundation in 1949, continued it during a brief visit to Liberia in 1952, and continued it again from 1959 to 1963. Primus' dissertation proposal, begun in 1959, was approved in 1975. Her doctorate was awarded in 1978 upon completion of the dissertation.
  - Proposal Drafts, 1959, 1975 and undated (Box 3)
  - Drafts, Chapters 1 and 2 (Box 3)
  - Drafts, Chapters 1-4, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Drafts, Foreword, Preface, Dedication (Box 3)
  - Through the Eyes of the Investigator (Box 3)
  - The Republic of Liberia, West Africa (Box 3)
  - Africa (Box 3)
  - Methodology (Chapter 3) (Box 3)
  - Ethnography (Chapter 4) (Box 3)
  - Dance (Chapter 4 of final dissertation) (Box 3)
  - The Enculturation Process Among the Mano People (Chapter 5) (Box 3)
  - When Sculpture-Danced Danced (Chapter 6) (Box 3)
  - Implications of the Study (Chapter 7) (Box 3)
  - Related Studies (Box 3)
  - Drafts, sections unidentified (Box 3)
  - Illustrations (Box 3)
  - Bibliography (Box 3)
  - Rosenwald Fellowship Correspondence, 1948-1960 (Box 3)
  - Dissertation-Related Correspondence, 1975-1977 and undated (Box 3)
  - Research Materials (Box 3)
  - Handwritten Notes and Drafts (Box 3)
- Printed Materials, circa 1935-1995, 4.3 linear feet (Box 3)
  Arranged chronolgically in two subseries: printed materials pertaining to Primus or her family members, and printed materials collected by Primus that do not specifically mention her or her family.
  - Primus and Family, circa 1940-1994 (Box 3)
    Contains programs, clippings, promotional materials, reviews, publications, announcements, flyers, press releases, and other items that specifically mention Primus or her immediate family, including Percival Borde and Onwin Primus-Borde, as well as performances of students Primus advised, groups she directed, dances she choreographed, and shows she lent costumes. Also included are articles and publications that Primus authored.
    - Program Drafts, circa 1940-1959 (Box OS1)
    - 1941-1960 (20 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1944-1985 (3 folders) (Box OS2)
    - 1961-1994 (32 folders) (Box 4)
  - Collected by Primus, circa 1935-1994 (Box 4)
    Contains printed materials that Primus collected but that do not specifically mention her or her family, including popular periodicals, newspaper clippings, programs, and brochures.
    - circa 1935-1994 (16 folders) (Box 4)
    - Rat newspaper, 1968 (Box OS2)
    - Master Class poster, 1974 or 1985 (Box OS3)
- Photographs, circa 1920-1992 and undated (Box OS3)
  - Prints, circa 1920-1992 and undated (Box OS3)
    Prints are arranged into four subseries: Portraits, Publicity, Performance, and Snapshots. Folder titles identify either the subject of the photo or the title of the dance depicted, followed by the date. When known, the photographer's name appears in parentheses.
    - Portraits, circa 1920-1992 (Box OS3)
      - Portraits of Primus, circa 1920-1992, 15 folders (Box OS3)
        - Primus, circa 1920 (Box 6)
        - Primus, circa 1930-1949 (2 folders) (Box 6)
        - Primus, circa 1940-1949 (Box 6)
        - Primus (Cris Alexander), circa 1940-1945 (3 folders) (Box 6)
        - Primus (Cris Alexander), circa 1940-1945 (Box OS2)
        - Primus (Gerda Peterich), circa 1940-1949 (Box 6)
        - Primus (Carl Van Vechten), circa 1940-1949 (Box 6)
        - Primus (photograph of painting by Robert G. Thomkins), 1950 (Box 6)
        - Primus (photograph of bust by Ben Karp), circa 1950-1959 (Box 6)
        - Primus, Percival, and Onwin Borde passport photos, circa 1961 (Box 6)
        - Primus, Afro-American Studies Department, University of Massachusetts-Amherst, 1992 (Box 6)
      - Portraits of Others, circa 1940-1969, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Others, signed or identified, circa 1940-1959 (Box 6)
        - Others, unidentified, circa 1940-1969 (Box 6)
    - Publicity, circa 1940-1969 (Box 6)
      - Primus in Performance, circa 1940-1959, 25 folders (Box 6)
        Arranged alphabetically by title of dance
        Contains publicity shots of Primus (sometimes with her company or family), depicting scenes from dance performances, taken by professional photographers for promotional purposes.
        - African Ceremonial (Gerda Peterich), circa 1944 (2 folders) (Box 6)
        - Afro-Haitian Play Dance (Gerda Peterich), circa 1940-1949 (Box 6)
        - Hard Times Blues, 1940 (Box OS2)
        - Dance of the Watusi, 1951 (Box 6)
        - Folk Dance, PM Daily Picture Magazine (Morris Gordon), 1944 (Box 6)
        - Folk Dance (Gerda Peterich), circa 1944 (Box 6)
        - Folk Dance (Jay Florian Mitchell), circa 1950-1959 (Box 6)
        - Folk Dance (Gerda Peterich), 1950-1959 (Box 6)
        - Negro Speaks of Rivers, circa 1940-1949 (3 folders) (Box 6)
        - Negro Speaks of Rivers, circa 1940-1949 (Box OS2)
        - Negro Speaks of Rivers (Gerda Peterich), circa 1940-1949 (2 folders) (Box 6)
        - Spirituals, circa 1940-1949 (Box 6)
        - Unidentified Dances, circa 1940-1959 (9 folders) (Box 7)
        - Unidentified Dances (Barbara Morgan), circa 1950-1959 (Box 7)
        - Unidentified Dances, with Joe Nash (Gerda Peterich), circa 1947 (Box 7)
      - Primus Company, circa 1940-1959, 11 folders (Box 7)
        Contains publicity shots of Primus company members in performance and in rehearsal.
        - Primus Company, circa 1940-1949 (2 folders) (Box 7)
        - Primus Company (Barry), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company (Barry), circa 1940-1949 (Box OS2)
        - Primus Company (Scurlock Studio), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company, Caribbean Conga (Gjon Mili), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company, Caribbean Conga (Jay Florian Mitchell), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company, Caribbean Conga (Jay Florian Mitchell), circa 1940-1949 (Box OS2)
        - Primus Company, Four Male Dancers (Marvin Smith), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company, Rehearsal (Gazelle Szabo), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company with Joe Nash and Jacqueline Hairston (Marvin Smith), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company, donkey costume (Jay Florian Mitchell), circa 1950-1955 (Box 7)
        - Primus Company, circa 1950-1959 (Box 7)
      - Public Appearances by Primus, circa 1940-1969, 40 folders (Box 7)
        Contains publicity shots taken at public appearances and events.
        - Radio appearance, circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Radio appearance, NBC (Dennis Stock), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Radio appearance, WHN (Irving Kaufman), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Saks Fifth Avenue Store Window (Worsinger), circa 1940-1949 (Box 7)
        - Appearances, circa 1940-1989 (Box 7)
        - War Effort, with CIO member/veterans, circa 1942-1944 (Box 7)
        - Cafe Society, circa 1943 (Box 7)
        - Emperor Jones, 1947 (Box 7)